<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Quantum Chemistry Group</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2025 Vamsee Voora</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>X-ray spectroscopy of molecules and liquids</title>
      <link>/project/xps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/xps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;X-ray spectroscopic techniques provide local electronic structure information by perturbing core-electrons. X-ray techniques such as XPS, XES and XAS provide information about local-oxidation states, nature of occupied/virtual orbitals, and nature of chemical bonding. These crucial techniques are receiving a leg-up from new generations of synchrotrons and X-ray free-electron lasers which are providing high intensity X-rays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are developing models to simulate and understand molecular and liquid-phase X-ray spectra using effective potential models based on the random phase approximation (RPA). These models do not depend on core-hole reference states, and hence overcome the issues with variational instability.  We also develop strategies to analyze the variations in core-electron binding energies by partitioning the RPA one-particle Hamiltonians.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charge mobility in organic materials</title>
      <link>/project/ips/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/ips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the crucial parameters that defines the performance of organic semiconducting materials is its charge carrier mobility. This intrinsic property is determined by temperature, crystallinity of the material, electronic and vibronic couplings. We are investigating new charge transport pathways due to diffuse electronic states that span several monomer units. These states may lead to larger electronic couplings and lower barriers to charge transfer. Our recent investigations have shown that such states are present in a variety of organic molecules ranging from halogenated aromatic systems to highly conjugated fullerene molecules. We are also investigating the role of underlying crystal structure in determining the electronic couplings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Structure Method Development</title>
      <link>/project/elec_struc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/elec_struc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To understand intermolecular interactions and one-electron properties we are developing post-Kohn-Sham (KS) approaches. The focus is on random phase approximation (RPA)-based methods that seamlessly incorporate van der Waals interactions to all orders and incorporate screening effects. The latter is particularly important as we tackle charge transfer processes in the regimes of molecular materials and liquids. We have formulated a generalized Kohn-Sham (GKS) scheme for a semi-canonical projected (sp) RPA that provides accurate energy and potential based properties such as intermolecular interaction energies and principal ionization potentials. Our initial results have shown that anions are correctly predicted to be stable within the GKS-spRPA scheme, which is currently a limitation for several semi-local functionals. We have also shown that accurate core-electron binding energies can be simulated using GKS-spRPA without any need for core-hole references states. Our current focus in this area involves extension of GKS-spRPA methods for X-ray spectroscopy and developing efficient algorithms that enable large-scale GKS-spRPA computational studies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
